<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://leowgordon.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://leowgordon.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-01-06T15:31:10+00:00</updated><id>https://leowgordon.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>The website of Leo W. Gordon. Find out about my projects and activities. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Hiring in the MR-e group</title><link href="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2025/PhD-Hiring/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hiring in the MR-e group"/><published>2025-09-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-09-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2025/PhD-Hiring</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2025/PhD-Hiring/"><![CDATA[<p>The MR-e group is hiring a PhD student to study energy materials (primarily electrolytes) using a combination of NMR spectroscopy and electrochemistry. The project involves using NMR methods to probe ion transport and ion interactions, in addition to developing operando methodologies to understand these phenomena further under non-equilibrium conditions. The deadline to apply is November 7th 2025. <a href="https://efzu.fa.em2.oraclecloud.com/hcmUI/CandidateExperience/en/sites/CX_2001/job/5903">Please view the posting for full details!</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Faculty"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The MR-e group is hiring a PhD student to study energy materials (primarily electrolytes) using a combination of NMR spectroscopy and electrochemistry. The project involves using NMR methods to probe ion transport and ion interactions, in addition to developing operando methodologies to understand these phenomena further under non-equilibrium conditions. The deadline to apply is November 7th 2025. Please view the posting (https://efzu.fa.em2.oraclecloud.com/hcmUI/CandidateExperience/en/sites/CX_2001/job/5903) for full details!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Starting as Assistant Professor in DTU Chemistry</title><link href="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2025/DTU/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Starting as Assistant Professor in DTU Chemistry"/><published>2025-08-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2025/DTU</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2025/DTU/"><![CDATA[<p>Today I have begun my faculty journey, starting as a new assistant professor in the chemistry department at the Danish Technical University (DTU). My group, the Magnetic Resonance and Electrochemistry (MR-e) Lab, will combine the worlds of magnetic resonance tools like NMR spectroscopy and MRI with electrochemical methods for the purpose of studying battery materials. Our goal is to build a deeper understanding of electrolytes by non-invasively probing them under non-equilibrium conditions, thereby enabling us to capture valuable insights of systems not at rest.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Faculty"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Today I have begun my faculty journey, starting as a new assistant professor in the chemistry department at the Danish Technical University (DTU). My group, the Magnetic Resonance and Electrochemistry (MR-e) Lab, will combine the worlds of magnetic resonance tools like NMR spectroscopy and MRI with electrochemical methods for the purpose of studying battery materials. Our goal is to build a deeper understanding of electrolytes by non-invasively probing them under non-equilibrium conditions, thereby enabling us to capture valuable insights of systems not at rest.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Two ACS Macro Letters Papers Published</title><link href="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2025/ACSML/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Two ACS Macro Letters Papers Published"/><published>2025-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2025/ACSML</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2025/ACSML/"><![CDATA[<p>Two separate co-author papers have just been published in ACS Macro Letters, <a href="10.1021/acsmacrolett.4c00707">one led by Rahul Sujanani</a>, and <a href="10.1021/acsmacrolett.4c00704">the other by James Bamford</a>. Rahul’s study investigates the influence of polymers under moderate hydration conditions, far from the well-studied extremes of rigorously dry, and highly swollen. In this we show the changes in conductivity and ion transport as a function of hydration, controlled by a bespoke setup, designed by Phong Ngyuen. This work demonstrates a crossover point in the relationship between hydration and conductivity that is defined by the hydration number of lithium ions. In James’ study, we show that lithium ion transport in a polymer with a pendant imidazole group can be improved by quaternization of the imidazole to imidazolium. This improvement is maintained even after T<sub>g</sub> normalisation, and is further punctuated by an inverse-Haven ratio greater than 1.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="papers"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Two separate co-author papers have just been published in ACS Macro Letters, one led by Rahul Sujanani, and the other by James Bamford. Rahul's study investigates the influence of polymers under moderate hydration conditions, far from the well-studied extremes of rigorously dry, and highly swollen. In this we show the changes in conductivity and ion transport as a function of hydration, controlled by a bespoke setup, designed by Phong Ngyuen. This work demonstrates a crossover point in the relationship between hydration and conductivity that is defined by the hydration number of lithium ions. In James' study, we show that lithium ion transport in a polymer with a pendant imidazole group can be improved by quaternization of the imidazole to imidazolium. This improvement is maintained even after Tg normalisation, and is further punctuated by an inverse-Haven ratio greater than 1.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Presentations at SCUM and AIChE</title><link href="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2024/SCUM-AIChE/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Presentations at SCUM and AIChE"/><published>2024-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2024/SCUM-AIChE</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2024/SCUM-AIChE/"><![CDATA[<p>In a very busy week, I had the opportunity to present at both the Southern California Users of Magnets (SCUM) meeting, and the American Institute for Chemical Engineers (AIChE) annual meeting. At SCUM 2024, I presented some of the new work from our group using spatially-resolved NMR methods for direct measurements of thermodynamic phenomena, namely partitioning. I demonstrated this capability through measurements of the octanol-water partitioning coefficients of different solutes, in addition to using NMR profilometry to visualise intensity maps of water moving across membranes. At AIChE, I was proposing my research vision as a faculty candidate. AIChE was an excellent opportunity to meet and network with my peers across a range of disciplines, I always cherish attending talks outside of my comfort zone! For anyone I met this week, please stay in touch. I’m always happy to discuss research, especially ways to incorporate NMR spectroscopy into your work!</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset=" /assets/img/AIChE_2024_poster-480.webp 480w, /assets/img/AIChE_2024_poster-800.webp 800w, /assets/img/AIChE_2024_poster-1400.webp 1400w, " sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/AIChE_2024_poster.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="500vw" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="conferences"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In a very busy week, I had the opportunity to present at both the Southern California Users of Magnets (SCUM) meeting, and the American Institute for Chemical Engineers (AIChE) annual meeting. At SCUM 2024, I presented some of the new work from our group using spatially-resolved NMR methods for direct measurements of thermodynamic phenomena, namely partitioning. I demonstrated this capability through measurements of the octanol-water partitioning coefficients of different solutes, in addition to using NMR profilometry to visualise intensity maps of water moving across membranes. At AIChE, I was proposing my research vision as a faculty candidate. AIChE was an excellent opportunity to meet and network with my peers across a range of disciplines, I always cherish attending talks outside of my comfort zone! For anyone I met this week, please stay in touch. I'm always happy to discuss research, especially ways to incorporate NMR spectroscopy into your work!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Harrison’s Electrochimica Acta Paper Published</title><link href="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2024/EchimActa/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Harrison’s Electrochimica Acta Paper Published"/><published>2024-10-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2024/EchimActa</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2024/EchimActa/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0013468624012684">A study borne from my PhD work</a> investigates the effects of mass transport and its interplay with electrochemical kinetics for aluminium-organic batteries. The study purports that there are two competing mechanisms in aluminum-quinone batteries, one that exists under high flux of intercalants, and the other under low flux. The mechanisms are dubbed concurrent and sequential, with these names relating to the ordering of the two-step electronic reduction and corresponding charge compensation. The concurrent mechanism occurs when the electrochemical Damköhler number is small (e.g., under high flux or low rates), and is ordered as electronic reduction-complexation-electronic reduction-complexation; the sequential mechanism by comparison occurs under conditions where the Damköhler number is large, and is ordered electronic reduction-electronic reduction-complexation-complexation. The key difference is that the uncompensated semiquinone form (after the first electronic reduction) is reduced at lower discharge potentials than the ionically compensated semiquinone. These mechanisms can be considered like putting on socks and shoes, you can go sock-shoe-sock-shoe (concurrent, small Da<sub>el</sub>), or sock-sock-shoe-shoe (sequential, large Da<sub>el</sub>). This study has consequences to any multielectronic organic electrodes, and tests multiple methods to affect Da<sub>el</sub>, all to the same conclusion.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="papers"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A study borne from my PhD work investigates the effects of mass transport and its interplay with electrochemical kinetics for aluminium-organic batteries. The study purports that there are two competing mechanisms in aluminum-quinone batteries, one that exists under high flux of intercalants, and the other under low flux. The mechanisms are dubbed concurrent and sequential, with these names relating to the ordering of the two-step electronic reduction and corresponding charge compensation. The concurrent mechanism occurs when the electrochemical Damköhler number is small (e.g., under high flux or low rates), and is ordered as electronic reduction-complexation-electronic reduction-complexation; the sequential mechanism by comparison occurs under conditions where the Damköhler number is large, and is ordered electronic reduction-electronic reduction-complexation-complexation. The key difference is that the uncompensated semiquinone form (after the first electronic reduction) is reduced at lower discharge potentials than the ionically compensated semiquinone. These mechanisms can be considered like putting on socks and shoes, you can go sock-shoe-sock-shoe (concurrent, small Dael), or sock-sock-shoe-shoe (sequential, large Dael). This study has consequences to any multielectronic organic electrodes, and tests multiple methods to affect Dael, all to the same conclusion.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ACS Applied Energy Materials Paper Published</title><link href="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2024/ACS-AEM/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ACS Applied Energy Materials Paper Published"/><published>2024-06-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2024/ACS-AEM</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2024/ACS-AEM/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acsaem.4c00739">An investigation</a> of eutectic electrolyte mixtures for low-temperature aluminium batteries led by Jonah Wang was published today. This work uses a combination of NMR spectroscopy and electrochemical methods to understand the electrolyte speciation and monitor the cycling performance, both for electrodeposition, and also in aluminium-graphite cells. We show operation down to -40 °C in the ternary AlCl<sub>3</sub>-urea-[EMIm]Cl mixture at a mole ratio of 1.3-0.25-0.75. In addition to supressing the freezing point, the addition of urea to the binary mixture of AlCl<sub>3</sub>-[EMIm]Cl improves the cost effectiveness of such electrolytes.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="papers"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An investigation of eutectic electrolyte mixtures for low-temperature aluminium batteries led by Jonah Wang was published today. This work uses a combination of NMR spectroscopy and electrochemical methods to understand the electrolyte speciation and monitor the cycling performance, both for electrodeposition, and also in aluminium-graphite cells. We show operation down to -40 &#8451 in the ternary AlCl3-urea-[EMIm]Cl mixture at a mole ratio of 1.3-0.25-0.75. In addition to supressing the freezing point, the addition of urea to the binary mixture of AlCl3-[EMIm]Cl improves the cost effectiveness of such electrolytes.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ACS Materials Letters Paper Published</title><link href="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2024/ACSML/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ACS Materials Letters Paper Published"/><published>2024-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2024/ACSML</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2024/ACSML/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/full/10.1021/acsmaterialslett.4c00531">We just published</a> a fundamental investigation of selenium structure at different length scales and how it affects the electrochemical reactions achieved in aluminium-selenium batteries. To achieve a full 6-electron capacity of selenium electrodes in aluminium batteries, it is imperative that the Se(0) to Se(–II) is attainable as well as the Se(0) to Se(IV) reactions. This paper documents the viability of the selenium to aluminium selenide electrochemical reduction in glassy selenium, which is seldom observed with crystalline trigonal selenium. This paper challenges the naive assumption that aluminium batteries using sulfur and selenium cathodes would operate in the same way. While both are chalcogens, the bonding topologies of elemental selenium and sulfur are quite different in their most stable forms (trigonal Se chains vs. 8-membered S rings) and this leads to differences in their electrochemical performances.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset=" /assets/img/Al-Se_ToC-480.webp 480w, /assets/img/Al-Se_ToC-800.webp 800w, /assets/img/Al-Se_ToC-1400.webp 1400w, " sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Al-Se_ToC.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="papers"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We just published a fundamental investigation of selenium structure at different length scales and how it affects the electrochemical reactions achieved in aluminium-selenium batteries. To achieve a full 6-electron capacity of selenium electrodes in aluminium batteries, it is imperative that the Se(0) to Se(–II) is attainable as well as the Se(0) to Se(IV) reactions. This paper documents the viability of the selenium to aluminium selenide electrochemical reduction in glassy selenium, which is seldom observed with crystalline trigonal selenium. This paper challenges the naive assumption that aluminium batteries using sulfur and selenium cathodes would operate in the same way. While both are chalcogens, the bonding topologies of elemental selenium and sulfur are quite different in their most stable forms (trigonal Se chains vs. 8-membered S rings) and this leads to differences in their electrochemical performances.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ACS Macro Letters Paper Published</title><link href="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2024/ACS-Macro-Letters/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ACS Macro Letters Paper Published"/><published>2024-05-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2024/ACS-Macro-Letters</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2024/ACS-Macro-Letters/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acsmacrolett.4c00158">Our recent paper</a> led by James Bamford demonstrates the improvements in mechanical strength after adding nickel salts to a coordinating, imidazole-containing polymer. The study demonstrates that even with addition of NiTFSI<sub>2</sub> up to r=0.16, ionic conductivity of Li<sup>+</sup> is not strongly affected, however, the increase in mechanical stiffness is notable as a result of dynamic crosslinking of imidazole functionalities with Ni<sup>2+</sup>. This demonstrates that ion transport and bulk mechanics can be decoupled by the addition of multivalent metal cations to polymers with chelating ligands.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset=" /assets/img/Imidazole-nickel-ToC-480.webp 480w, /assets/img/Imidazole-nickel-ToC-800.webp 800w, /assets/img/Imidazole-nickel-ToC-1400.webp 1400w, " sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Imidazole-nickel-ToC.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="250vw" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="papers"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Our recent paper led by James Bamford demonstrates the improvements in mechanical strength after adding nickel salts to a coordinating, imidazole-containing polymer. The study demonstrates that even with addition of NiTFSI2 up to r=0.16, ionic conductivity of Li+ is not strongly affected, however, the increase in mechanical stiffness is notable as a result of dynamic crosslinking of imidazole functionalities with Ni2+. This demonstrates that ion transport and bulk mechanics can be decoupled by the addition of multivalent metal cations to polymers with chelating ligands.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Advanced Energy Materials Paper Published</title><link href="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2024/AEM/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Advanced Energy Materials Paper Published"/><published>2024-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2024/AEM</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2024/AEM/"><![CDATA[<p>Recently a <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/aenm.202303285">collaborative work</a> with Oi-Man Leung at the Unversity of Southampton was published in Advanced Energy Materials. This study represents a culmination of efforts on both the electrochemistry and applications of this new electrolyte, and also the mechanistic analyses to elucidate the molecular-scale processes within. Here, we demonstrate a huge 0.3 V improvement in the oxidative stability vs. the standard AlCl<sub>3</sub>-EMIm ionic liquid electrolyte. This increase is coupled with the inherent mechanical improvements of a polymer electrolyte, without any major sacrifice of the electrolyte conductivity. NMR spectroscopy reveals AlCl<sub>3</sub> crosslinks between poly(ethylene oxide) (PEO) chains and some curious behvaiour of silica particles in this system…</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="papers"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Recently a collaborative work with Oi-Man Leung at the Unversity of Southampton was published in Advanced Energy Materials. This study represents a culmination of efforts on both the electrochemistry and applications of this new electrolyte, and also the mechanistic analyses to elucidate the molecular-scale processes within. Here, we demonstrate a huge 0.3 V improvement in the oxidative stability vs. the standard chloroaluminate ionic liquid electrolyte. This increase is coupled with the inherent mechanical improvements of a polymer electrolyte, without any major sacrifice of the electrolyte conductivity. NMR spectroscopy reveals aluminium chloride crosslinks between poly(ethylene oxide) (PEO) chains and some curious behvaiour of silica particles in this system...]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PhD Defense</title><link href="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2023/FinalExam/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PhD Defense"/><published>2023-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2023/FinalExam</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2023/FinalExam/"><![CDATA[<p>Today I sucessfully defended my PhD thesis “Molecular Elucidation of Reaction Mechanisms in Aluminum and Lithium Metal Batteries by Solid-State NMR Spectroscopy and Electrochemical Methods”. My PhD journey has been a greatly enjoyable 5 years and I have far too many people to thank for getting me to this point. However, I must acknowledge my committee members, Prof. Alex Couzis, Prof. Ruth Stark, Prof. George John, Prof. Elizabeth Biddinger, and my advisor Prof. Robert Messinger for their great support today. Special thanks to Rob for all the hard work we put in together!</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset=" /assets/img/Defense-480.webp 480w, /assets/img/Defense-800.webp 800w, /assets/img/Defense-1400.webp 1400w, " sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Defense.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="PhD-Progression"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Today I sucessfully defended my PhD thesis "Molecular Elucidation of Reaction Mechanisms in Aluminum and Lithium Metal Batteries by Solid-State NMR Spectroscopy and Electrochemical Methods". My PhD journey has been a greatly enjoyable 5 years and I have far too many people to thank for getting me to this point. However, I must acknowledge my committee members, Prof. Alex Couzis, Prof. Ruth Stark, Prof. George John, Prof. Elizabeth Biddinger, and my advisor Prof. Robert Messinger for their great support today. Special thanks to Rob for all the hard work we put in together!]]></summary></entry></feed>