<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://leowgordon.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://leowgordon.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-05-28T18:31:46+00:00</updated><id>https://leowgordon.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>The website of Leo W. Gordon. Find out about my projects and activities. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">ACS Materials Letters Paper Published</title><link href="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2024/ACSML/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ACS Materials Letters Paper Published"/><published>2024-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2024/ACSML</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2024/ACSML/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/full/10.1021/acsmaterialslett.4c00531">We just published</a> a fundamental investigation of selenium structure at different length scales and how it affects the electrochemical reactions achieved in aluminium-selenium batteries. To achieve a full 6-electron capacity of selenium electrodes in aluminium batteries, it is imperative that the Se(0) to Se(–II) is attainable as well as the Se(0) to Se(IV) reactions. This paper documents the viability of the selenium to aluminium selenide electrochemical reduction in glassy selenium, which is seldom observed with crystalline trigonal selenium. This paper challenges the naive assumption that aluminium batteries using sulfur and selenium cathodes would operate in the same way. While both are chalcogens, the bonding topologies of elemental selenium and sulfur are quite different in their most stable forms (trigonal Se chains vs. 8-membered S rings) and this leads to differences in their electrochemical performances.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset=" /assets/img/Al-Se_ToC-480.webp 480w, /assets/img/Al-Se_ToC-800.webp 800w, /assets/img/Al-Se_ToC-1400.webp 1400w, " sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Al-Se_ToC.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="papers"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We just published a fundamental investigation of selenium structure at different length scales and how it affects the electrochemical reactions achieved in aluminium-selenium batteries. To achieve a full 6-electron capacity of selenium electrodes in aluminium batteries, it is imperative that the Se(0) to Se(–II) is attainable as well as the Se(0) to Se(IV) reactions. This paper documents the viability of the selenium to aluminium selenide electrochemical reduction in glassy selenium, which is seldom observed with crystalline trigonal selenium. This paper challenges the naive assumption that aluminium batteries using sulfur and selenium cathodes would operate in the same way. While both are chalcogens, the bonding topologies of elemental selenium and sulfur are quite different in their most stable forms (trigonal Se chains vs. 8-membered S rings) and this leads to differences in their electrochemical performances.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Advanced Energy Materials Paper Published</title><link href="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2024/AEM/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Advanced Energy Materials Paper Published"/><published>2024-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2024/AEM</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2024/AEM/"><![CDATA[<p>Recently a <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/aenm.202303285">collaborative work</a> with Oi-Man Leung at the Unversity of Southampton was published in Advanced Energy Materials. This study represents a culmination of efforts on both the electrochemistry and applications of this new electrolyte, and also the mechanistic analyses to elucidate the molecular-scale processes within. Here, we demonstrate a huge 0.3 V improvement in the oxidative stability vs. the standard AlCl<sub>3</sub>-EMIm ionic liquid electrolyte. This increase is coupled with the inherent mechanical improvements of a polymer electrolyte, without any major sacrifice of the electrolyte conductivity. NMR spectroscopy reveals AlCl<sub>3</sub> crosslinks between poly(ethylene oxide) (PEO) chains and some curious behvaiour of silica particles in this system…</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="papers"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Recently a collaborative work with Oi-Man Leung at the Unversity of Southampton was published in Advanced Energy Materials. This study represents a culmination of efforts on both the electrochemistry and applications of this new electrolyte, and also the mechanistic analyses to elucidate the molecular-scale processes within. Here, we demonstrate a huge 0.3 V improvement in the oxidative stability vs. the standard chloroaluminate ionic liquid electrolyte. This increase is coupled with the inherent mechanical improvements of a polymer electrolyte, without any major sacrifice of the electrolyte conductivity. NMR spectroscopy reveals aluminium chloride crosslinks between poly(ethylene oxide) (PEO) chains and some curious behvaiour of silica particles in this system...]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PhD Defense</title><link href="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2023/FinalExam/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PhD Defense"/><published>2023-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2023/FinalExam</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2023/FinalExam/"><![CDATA[<p>Today I sucessfully defended my PhD thesis “Molecular Elucidation of Reaction Mechanisms in Aluminum and Lithium Metal Batteries by Solid-State NMR Spectroscopy and Electrochemical Methods”. My PhD journey has been a greatly enjoyable 5 years and I have far too many people to thank for getting me to this point. However, I must acknowledge my committee members, Prof. Alex Couzis, Prof. Ruth Stark, Prof. George John, Prof. Elizabeth Biddinger, and my advisor Prof. Robert Messinger for their great support today. Special thanks to Rob for all the hard work we put in together!</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset=" /assets/img/Defense-480.webp 480w, /assets/img/Defense-800.webp 800w, /assets/img/Defense-1400.webp 1400w, " sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Defense.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="PhD-Progression"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Today I sucessfully defended my PhD thesis "Molecular Elucidation of Reaction Mechanisms in Aluminum and Lithium Metal Batteries by Solid-State NMR Spectroscopy and Electrochemical Methods". My PhD journey has been a greatly enjoyable 5 years and I have far too many people to thank for getting me to this point. However, I must acknowledge my committee members, Prof. Alex Couzis, Prof. Ruth Stark, Prof. George John, Prof. Elizabeth Biddinger, and my advisor Prof. Robert Messinger for their great support today. Special thanks to Rob for all the hard work we put in together!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Journal of Physical Chemistry Letters Paper Published</title><link href="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2023/JPCL/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Journal of Physical Chemistry Letters Paper Published"/><published>2023-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2023/JPCL</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2023/JPCL/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acs.jpclett.3c00150">The latest work from our group</a> “Reversible Zinc Electrodeposition at −60 °C Using a Deep Eutectic Electrolyte for Low-Temperature Zinc Metal Batteries” was published today. In this work we demonstrate an electrolyte with a deep-eutectic point to enable reversible zinc electrodeposition down to temperatures of -60 °C. We make 0.1 M Zn(TFSI)<sub>2</sub> electrolytes in different ratios of [EMIm]TFSI with gamma-butyrolactone (GBL) which are probed electrochemically to determine their macroscopic properties, and further analysed at the molecular level via NMR spectroscopy and molecular dynamics (MD) simulations to explain the differences in performance from an atomistic approach.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="papers"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The latest work from our group "Reversible Zinc Electrodeposition at −60 &#8451 Using a Deep Eutectic Electrolyte for Low-Temperature Zinc Metal Batteries" was published today. In this work we demonstrate an electrolyte with a deep-eutectic point to enable reversible zinc electrodeposition down to temperatures of -60 &#8451. We make electrolytes in different ratios of [EMIm]TFSI with gamma-butyrolactone (GBL) which are probed electrochemically to determine their macroscopic properties, and further analysed at the molecular level via NMR spectroscopy and molecular dynamics (MD) simulations to explain the differences in performance from an atomistic approach.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Journal of Magnetic Resonance Paper Published</title><link href="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2023/JMR/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Journal of Magnetic Resonance Paper Published"/><published>2023-01-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2023/JMR</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2023/JMR/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S1090780723000095">Our new study</a> of aluminium-organic batteries, entitled “Revealing Impacts of Electrolyte Speciation on Ionic Charge Storage in Aluminum-Quinone Batteries by NMR Spectroscopy”, is now out in the Journal of Magnetic Resonance. This is a detailed analysis of the ionic charge storage mechanisms in aluminium-quinone batteries where we begin by detailing the speciation of three different Lewis acidic ionic liquid/ionic liquid analogue electrolytes by liquid-state NMR, we then use solid-state NMR to determine the nature of the complexed ions upon electrochemical discharge in each electrolyte. We further use DFT calculations to both determine the most favorable electroactive cation generation pathways and to link the experimentally derived NMR quadrupolar parameters to a physical basis of ion interaction with different quinone structures. Finally, we also validate our hypothesised mechanisms with targeted experiments, proving the function of various ionic species.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset=" /assets/img/DCQ_ToC_Figure-480.webp 480w, /assets/img/DCQ_ToC_Figure-800.webp 800w, /assets/img/DCQ_ToC_Figure-1400.webp 1400w, " sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/DCQ_ToC_Figure.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="papers"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Our new study of aluminium-organic batteries, entitled "Revealing Impacts of Electrolyte Speciation on Ionic Charge Storage in Aluminum-Quinone Batteries by NMR Spectroscopy", is now out in the Journal of Magnetic Resonance. This is a detailed analysis of the ionic charge storage mechanisms in aluminium-quinone batteries where we begin by detailing the speciation of three different Lewis acidic ionic liquid or ionic liquid analogue electrolytes by liquid-state NMR, we then use solid-state NMR to determine the nature of the complexed ions upon electrochemical discharge in each electrolyte. We further use DFT calculations to both determine the most favorable electroactive cation generation pathways and to link the experimentally derived NMR quadrupolar parameters to a physical basis of ion interaction with different quinone structures. Finally, we also validate our hypothesised mechanisms with targeted experiments, proving the function of various ionic species.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">BES 2022</title><link href="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2022/BES/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="BES 2022"/><published>2022-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2022/BES</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2022/BES/"><![CDATA[<p>The 4th battery and energy storage conference, taking place this year in CUNY’s very own Advanced Science and Research Center building, was a fast-paced and highly engaging few days. Great talks from many people with a variety of topics - from space applications, to cutting edge recycling techniques.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="conferences"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The 4th battery and energy storage conference, taking place this year in CUNY's very own Advanced Science and Research Center building, was a fast-paced and highly engaging few days. Great talks from many people with a variety of topics - from space applications, to cutting edge recycling techniques.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ECS 2022</title><link href="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2022/ECS/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ECS 2022"/><published>2022-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2022/ECS</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2022/ECS/"><![CDATA[<p>ECS 2022 was a nice conference with lots of engaging talks, including from Nobel Laureate Prof. Stan Whittingham, who even stopped by the student mixer to mingle with the student members of ECS. It was great to meet a lot of new people, especially finally being able to meet people in person.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="conferences"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[ECS 2022 was a nice conference with lots of engaging talks, including from Nobel Laureate Prof. Stan Whittingham, who even stopped by the student mixer to mingle with the student members of ECS. It was great to meet a lot of new people, especially finally being able to meet people in person.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Journal of Physical Chemistry C Paper Published</title><link href="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2022/JPCC/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Journal of Physical Chemistry C Paper Published"/><published>2022-08-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-08-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2022/JPCC</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2022/JPCC/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acs.jpcc.2c04272">My debut first-author paper</a> came out today, “Molecular-Scale Elucidation of Ionic Charge Storage Mechanisms in Rechargeable Aluminum–Quinone Batteries”. This study puts forward an in-depth analysis of charge storage mechanisms in aluminium-quinone batteries that we expect to be generalisable for all anthraquinone-based materials paired with aluminium-metal anodes in Lewis acidic AlCl<sub>3</sub>:[EMIm]Cl electrolyte. We used a combination of electrochemical analyses with mutlidimensional solid-state NMR techniques to develop a mechanistic understanding of electronic and ionic charge storage in Al-quinone batteries culminating in a detailed chemical reaction scheme. We also highlight a potential pitfall in sample harvesting and solid-state NMR methods to overcome this challenge.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="papers"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My debut first-author paper came out today, "Molecular-Scale Elucidation of Ionic Charge Storage Mechanisms in Rechargeable Aluminum–Quinone Batteries". This study puts forward an in-depth analysis of charge storage mechanisms in aluminium-quinone batteries that we expect to be generalisable for all anthraquinone-based materials paired with aluminium-metal anodes in Lewis acidic chloroaluminate electrolyte.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ACS Applied Materials &amp;amp; Interfaces Paper Published</title><link href="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2022/ACS-Appl-Mat-Int/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ACS Applied Materials &amp;amp; Interfaces Paper Published"/><published>2022-08-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-08-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2022/ACS-Appl-Mat-Int</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2022/ACS-Appl-Mat-Int/"><![CDATA[<p>Our paper in collaboration with the Juchen Guo group (UC Riverside): “Performance Leap of Lithium Metal Batteries in LiPF<sub>6</sub> Carbonate Electrolyte by a Phosphorus Pentoxide Acid Scavenger” was published in ACS Applied Materials &amp; Interfaces today. This work is a culmination of excellent performance of lithium metal batteries and deep, mechanistic understanding. We go beyond just showing the long cycle lifetimes achieved by the addition of P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> and show the SEI composition, the electrolyte species present, and develop a feasible reaction mechanism to describe the pathway to producing the moieties responsible for the performance enhancement. The paper can be accessed <a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/acsami.2c09267">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="papers"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Our paper in collaboration with the Juchen Guo group (UC Riverside)&#58; "Performance Leap of Lithium Metal Batteries in LiPF6 Carbonate Electrolyte by a Phosphorus Pentoxide Acid Scavenger" was published in ACS Applied Materials & Interfaces today. This work is a culmination of excellent performance of lithium metal batteries and deep, mechanistic understanding.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Global NMR Discussions Twitter Conference 2022</title><link href="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2022/Twitter-Conference/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Global NMR Discussions Twitter Conference 2022"/><published>2022-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2022/Twitter-Conference</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leowgordon.github.io/blog/2022/Twitter-Conference/"><![CDATA[<p>I presented a poster at the Global NMR discussions Twitter conference and had a good time learning some new things and engaging with some more of the NMR community.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="conferences"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I presented a poster at the Global NMR discussions Twitter conference and had a good time learning some new things and engaging with some more of the NMR community.]]></summary></entry></feed>